Hello, and welcome to week three of our class on image and video processing.
大家好 欢迎来到图像和视频处理第三周的课程
What you're seeing right now is me in a relatively dark room.
你们现在看到 我在一个非常暗的房间里
You can probably see the Duke Chapel behind me but you can't see details, for
你们应该可以看到我身后的杜克教堂 但是有一些细节你们是看不到的
example, the color of the shirt I'm wearing.
比如说我身上穿的衣服的颜色
Or, if you were to look at my desk, it's basically very dark, and you can't see
或者看向我的桌子 这里非常的暗 你们基本上看不到什么
much. What happen when we take an image like
如果我们拿到这样一张图像要怎么处理？
this? What happen when we have a video that is
如果我们拿到一个背景非常暗的视频又要怎么处理？
very dark? That happens us all the time, we take a
我们在晚上拍照的时候 这种情况经常发生
picture at night. Doesn't have the lighting that we want.
或者没有理想的采光
It's too dark or too bright, sometimes too noisy.
图像就可能太暗或者太亮 有时候噪点太多
What we are going to do during this week is to learn how to improve those images.
我们这周要学的就是如何改善这些图像
How to enhance those images. We're going to start with very simple
如何进行图像增强 我们从最简单的操作开始
manipulations. That will basically help us to improve
这些操作会帮助提高对比度
the contrast, remove the noise. And we're going to go towards the end of
消除噪点 我们在本周最后的课程
the week to more advanced techniques. Which are basically leading to state of
会讲一些更先进的技术 这些都是现今最顶尖的技术
the art approaches today. And we're going to come back to some
而在课程的最后
these towards the end of the class to basically week seven, week eight, to
大概是第七周或第八周的时候 我们也会回过头来
really, really advance techniques for image enhancement.
讲解图像增强中非常非常前沿的技术
During this week and during the following weeks we're also going to do online and
在这周和下周中 我们还会做一些线上的实时演示
real time demos so I'm going to basically teach you some of the material and then
在这里我会教你们一些背景知识
we're going to run some different software platforms to basically do some
然后我们一起运行一些不同的软件平台 来实践一下这些操作
of these operations. Right now on my PC, and you are going to
就在我的电脑上 大家可以看到
see them, in practice, how they are working.
它们在实践中如何操作的
We're also going to introduce some online video quizzes so, basically I'm going to
我们还会介绍一些在线的视频小测试
pause for a second and you're going to be able to think about a question that I
我会在视频中有些停顿 这样大家就可以思考一下我提的问题
will post to you. That won't basically affect your, your
这并不会对大家最后拿到证书产生影响
certificate at the end but it's just to have you think for a while before I give
我只是想要给大家一点时间
you the answer to the question, like in any regular class that I will basically
在我给出答案前思考这些问题 就像平时上课一样
pause to have the students think for a minute.
我会停下让学生们来想一想
Before we continue let me turn on the lights so I can continue this and write.
我先去把灯打开 再来给大家讲课和板书
And explain to you the basic principles of image enhancement and contrast
并给大家解释图像增强、对比度增强
enhancement and image you're now seeing. So bear with me for a second.
以及图像去噪的基本原理 所以大家等我一下
I'm going to turn on my lights and we will be right back.
我去开个灯 马上就回来
So now I'm turning the lights on. So you can see.
现在我把灯打开了 大家就能看到一些细节了
A bit of the details. you can't see much in the background
大家可能看不太清背景了
anymore but you can see what's in the room.
但是可以看到屋内的东西
And what I'm going to show you is how we turn the lights on, digitally, in the
我要给大家讲的就是如何在电脑中用数字化方式开灯
computer. So you have taken your image.
所以如果照片已经照好了
You can now go back to SIM. I want to turn the lights on with image
大家又不能回到之前的场景重新照
processing and video processing software so let's start doing that.
我想要利用图像和视频处理软件来“开灯” 现在我们就要开始了
And we basically are going to start from very simple operations, which are
我们要从非常简单的操作开始
histogram modifications, or pointwise operations.
都是一些直方图修正 或者说是逐点运算
So, the basic idea is illustrated in this figure.
这个图表明了它的基本思想
Every pixel of the image, it's going to change it's own value,
图像中的每一个像素 都会根据一个特定的方程
following certain function. So.
改变它的值 因此
The pixel here will move to a new image where basically it changed its value but
这里的像素值会改变并移动到一个新的图像中
it will change its value only based on its own value right now.
但它只会根据自身的像素值来改变
It's not going to be influenced by anything that's happening in any other
而不会被图像中其它任何部分的像素影响到
part of the image. That's the first part of this week three.
这是第三周课程中的第一部分
We're going to see later how we basically influence the pixel value by other things
后面我们将了解如何利用图像中的其它信息改变像素值
that are happening in the image. But to start, very simple, what's called
但我们要先从非常简单的逐点运算开始
point-wise operations. There's a certain pixel value in, in the
这里输入值是一个特定的像素值
input, a certain pixel value in the output.
输出值也是一个特定的像素值
Similarly here. For example, what's happening here is
这里也一样 例如这个运算中
that everybody up to pixel value K. Becomes zero, everybody above K becomes
所有小于 k 的像素值都会变成 0 而大于k 的像素值会变成 1
one or the maximum value. In the image.
或者是图像中的最大值
So this is basically a thresh holding operation.
这里进行了 阈值处理
So, what we need to specify, is it one dimensional function, that translates the
所以现在要确立一个一维函数
input to the output. And, let's just see, a few examples of
来将输入值转化为输出值 现在大家来看看一下几个例子
that. So here we see a few illustrations of
这里有一些图示
this. Several of these operations, inverse log.
一些变换操作 比如反对数
Of course lets start from the identity. The input is identical to the output.
当然我们先从恒等变换开始 输入值与输出值相等
So basically this is the identity. If we basically mark the output as S.
这就是恒等变换 如果我们把输出值写作 s
An entity is S = R. The output is identical to the input.
那么正比函数的表达式是 s = r 输出值等于输入值
We have done nothing to the image. We also have a log operation.
我们没有改变图像 还有对数运算
For example the output is some constant times the log of the input, and we
比如输出值是一个常数乘以输入值的对数
normally are going to add let's say 1. Because if the input is 0, we cannot take
我们一般会加1 因为如果输入是0
the logarithmic of zero. So we do we this.
我们就没有办法取0的对数 所以我们这样处理
So that's an hour operation. Whatever is the grade value of the input
这就是要做的运算 不管输入的灰度值是什么
we transform it to the output. There is also the inverse, which is
我们都会将其转化为输出值 还有反转 画在了这里
written here. And I want to, I want for you to think
我想让大家想一下
for a second, what will be basically the function that will represent the inverse.
什么函数可以表示反转
Considering that our image goes from 0 to L.
考虑到图像中的值是从0到L的
So the minimal value is 0, the maximum value is L.
最小值是0 最大值是L
While would be the function, basically I want to write S.
函数会是什么样的呢？ 我想把 s 写成
As a function of r. Why would be that function that will
一个关于 r 的函数
basically do the negation of the image. The maximal value of the input will
怎样的函数才能对图像进行反转？
become zero. And the minimal value of the input
输入的最大值会变成0 而最小值也就是0
meaning zero would become L. So let's just think for a second and it's
会变成 L 所以大家来想一下
a very simple exercise just to illustrate how simple.
这是一个非常简单的练习 用来展示一下
And as we are going to see in a second, how powerful at the same time, these type
这种运算有多么简单 并且我们等一下会看到 它又是多么强大
of operations are. So, we know that, basically, I ask you
现在我问问大家
how to, basically, construct this function?
如何构建这个函数
And it's very simple. We want the output to be the inverse.
这非常简单 我们想要输出值成为输入值的反转
of the input, so S equal L, the maximum value minus R.
那么 s = L - r 其中 L为最大值
So when R is L, S becomes zero because its L minus L.
这样当 r等于 L的时候 s就会变成0 即 L-L
When R is zero, then basically S become L, which is the maximum.
当r等于0 那么s就变成了L 也就是最大值
So, a very, very simple operation that just involves our great values.
所以这是一个非常非常简单的将灰度值反转的运算
And note, that all what occur in all of these operations, is the actual great
注意 这里所有的运算 实际上都只关心灰度值
value. I'm not asking where's the pixel located
这里并不关心像素在图像中的位置
in the image? I'm just asking what's the pixel value?
而只关心像素值
What's the great value of that image? So, here is one example of this.
只关心图像的灰度值是多少 这里有一个例子
Basically this function that we just wrote S equal L minus R is basically
我们刚才写的这个 s = L-r 的方程
taking every pixel and doing the inversion so it's the negative image and
取了所有像素的反转值 所以会得到反转图像
some of the things that we see is that is basically easier for us to.
我们可以看到
See just visually some of the things in the negative image than it is.
有一些细节在反转图像中比在原图中更容易辨认
In that original image. And why is this?
这是为什么？
Remember early on we talk about the properties of the visual system that
记得之前我们讨论过视觉系统的一些特点
there are certain contrast that we understand better.
我们对于某些对比更加敏感
That we perceive better at different levels of the background.
在不同的背景下我们可以看得更加清楚
And we saw that there are some contrasts that are perceived better when we are in
我们看到了有一些对比在深色区域下更加清晰
the dark regions. Some contrasts are perceived differently
而有一些对比在浅色区域中会显得不同
when we are in the light regions. So, this inversion, basically, might help
所以图像反转 可能会帮助我们
us to perceive things that are difficult to notice in the original image.
看清在原图中很难注意到的东西
Very simple illustration. One other important thing of these type
这是很简单的例子 这些操作还有一个重要性质
of operations is, I can go back. So, if I start from here, I have not
即这些运算是可逆的 如果从这里开始
destroyed the information. I can simply go back and reverse this
我们并没有破坏任何信息 因而可以做简单的逆向运算回到原图
operation, that's not always possible as we're going to see later this week.
我们在这周后续课程中会看到 这并不总是可行的
But, for this particular operation that is doable.
但是这种特殊的运算是可以的
Another extremely important operation is basically an exponential function, and
另外一个非常重要的运算是指数函数
I'm going to write it here S, the output is going to be a constant, the input, to
我写在这里 输出值s 会变成一个常数乘以输入值的 γ次方
some exponent, gamma, and the basic idea here is that depending on, gamma in
这里的基本思路是 根据特定的 γ
particular we get different functions, that transforms the input, to the output,
我们会得到不同的函数 来将输入值转换成输出值
and this is very often called gamma correction.
通常把这称作伽马校正
And this actually is very popular. In monitors, because of some properties
这是一个在显示器中非常常用的函数 由于显示器的一些特性
of the monitor, if you don't do a gamma correction to your image, your image is
如果不对图像做伽马校正
going to look relatively dark. So, if this is.
那么图像会显得特别暗 所以如果这是我的图像
My image its going to look dark, and it's going be hard to perceive exactly the
那么它会变得非常暗 这样会很难看清其中的细节
details. And that's because of the properties of
这是显示器的一些特性造成的
the monitor. So sometimes before you send the image to
所以有时在将图片发送到显示器之前
the display to the monitor you do what's called a gamma correction.
需要做伽马校正
So you gamma correct the image, and then you basically send it to the display.
如果对图像做了伽马校正 再发送到显示屏
And what's basically the gamma correction is doing is inverting this.
伽马校正就会抵消
Darkening operation that happens due to some properties in the monitor.
由于显示器的特性而产生的变暗的效果
So it's a very useful, very common operation.
所以这是非常有用并且非常常见的运算
Basically shows up. In virtually every monitor there is a
基本上每个显示器
gamma correction before the image is basically display.
在显示之前都会做伽马校正
But gamma correction or basically this exponential function is very useful in
但是伽马校正 或者说这个指数函数
general to basically kind of stretch if you need the pixel values.
一般来说 在延展像素值时 也非常有用
Remember we have instagrams and. Which are the distributions of the
还记得直方图吧 它显示了像素的分布
pixels. And, for example, if we look at this
例如 我们来看看这个图像
image it looks like most of the pixels are concentrated on the bright values.
大多数的像素会聚集在较亮的值上
So, if we were to draw, and we're going to do.
如果我们要画直方图
This. This event.
我们以后会经常画直方图
Very often, basically starting, in the next in the next video, but allowed in
基本上从下个视频开始 这周会画很多直方图
this way. So, probably, if we were to plug the
所以 如果我们要画这个图像的像素分布
distribution of the pixel values of this image, there would occupy a lot, this
那么在这个区域的像素会占很多
region. Because we look like the image is
因为我们可以看到这个图像中
basically too much of the high values, very bright.
有很多高像素值的点 画面很亮
So, with gamma corrections, we can manage to actually stretch this histogram and
所以有了伽马校正 我们就可以延展这个直方图
this are just different values, but I think the simplest is to just look at
这里用了不同的 γ 值 但是我认为这张图最直观
this one. And we see that we have basically a nicer
首先 我们可以看到这里生成了一个更好的图像
image it looks better than this image first of all.
比这个图像看起来要好
But it also helps us to better understand some of the details and I hope that you
并且它还会帮助我们更好地看清一些细节
can still in your own monitor that it's doing its own gamma correction.
虽然大家的显示器中都在做各自的伽马校正 但我希望你们都能看得清楚
Then you can actually perceive better, details here, details here, and in
所以大家可以更清楚地看到这里、这里和其它不同区域中的细节
different regions in the image. And sometimes, it might become too much,
有时候可能校正过度
so you might do a different type of gamma.
所以大家可能会选择不同的 γ 值来做伽马校正
So you might say oh, this region actually, I'm not.
大家可能会觉得 这个区域
... Perceiving a lot of the details.
有很多细节其实看不清
So maybe I should a different value of gamma as illustrated here.
所以或许大家会用另外一个 γ 值 就像这里展示的
This are researches of different values of gamma.
这些是用不同 γ 值得出的图像
And you could actually do some of these operations not in the whole image but in
大家可以只对图像的一些区域做这些运算
some regions of the image. So you can invert only some region of the
而不用应用到整个图像 大家可以只对图像的一些区域做反转
image. You can do a gamma correction or an
也可以只对图像的一些区域
exponential function in only some regions of the image.
做伽马校正或者使用指数函数
So you don't have to do them every place. You can do them locally.
大家并不用将这些运算应用在所有地方 可以只在局部应用
So that's. A very simple operation, that immediately
所以这是一个非常简单的运算
gives us a much nicer perception of the image.
并且可以立即给我们一个更清晰的图像
Remember the video, as we started this video, was very dark.
记住在这个视频开端 我的视频是非常暗的
That means that the distribution, basically peaks of values.
这就意味着像素值的分布
Were around here. If this is the histogram distribution and
是集中在这里的 如果这是直方图分布
this kind of operation help us to stretch to basically use better the resources
这种运算会帮助我们延展这个分布
that we have in the display to use the whole spectrum of values from 0 to 255
这样会更好地利用显示屏中的资源 可以用到0到255整个范围
instead of just using the dark part of the values or only the bright part of the
而不仅仅是较暗或者较亮部分的值
values. Again a very, very simple operation.
再次强调 这是一个非常非常简单的运算
here there is a lot of art in designing of these operations but with experience
这些运算的设计中有很多技巧
we understand what we need to do. Here is yet in our example of the
但是有了经验 我们会慢慢理解需要做什么
stretching of the pixel values. So once again this is the input, this is
这里是另外一个像素值拉伸的例子 这里依旧是输入值 r
R, this is S, this is the output. So if your pixel values are between this
这里是输出值s 如果你的像素值是在
point and this point not a lot is happening.
这个点和这个点之间 那么基本上不会发生什么
Okay. So this is going to be the original
这里是原图像
image. Pixels values that are relatively dark,
比较暗的像素值不会有什么变化
not a lot is going to happen to it, then. Pixels that are relatively bright.
比较亮的像素值也不会有什么变化
Not a lot is going to happen to them but pickus value in between are going to be
而介于中间的像素值
stretch basically I'm going to, this has slope much larger than one.
会被拉伸 它的斜率远大于 1
If the slope was one, nothing will happen to them.
如果斜率是1 那么像素会保持不变
If the slope is less than one, it would be basic contracted.
如果斜率小于1 相当于像素值被压缩
If the slope is larger than one, it would be stretched.
如果斜率大于1 就会被拉伸
Okay? So if we have slope larger than one, zero
如果我们有一个大于1的斜率
stays zero. But one basically goes up to the slope
0还是0 但是1会被拉伸 增加到斜率值
and gets stretched. And then we see what happened.
我们来看看这个效果
This is the retaliament because the mid-range of the pixel values gets
这是原图像 因为中间区域的像素值被延展了
stretched. All of a sudden, I can see details that I
大家就能突然看清之前无法辨识的细节了
couldn't see before. Look at the points here are extremely
仔细观察这里非常难注意到的点
difficult to notice, but here I can see that actually there were spots in this
在这里却能够看到这张图像在这里是有斑点的
image. And then if you wish you can threshold
大家如果想的话 可以对图像做阈值处理
that image and that's whats happened here so we can distinguish the different
就像这里做的一样 然后大家就可以分辨不同的区域
regions. But notice the difference of going from
但是注意从这里到这里的变化
here to here, very hard to understand. What's happening here?
这里非常难看清图像内容
Much nicer looking image here, not only much nicer looking, but I can also see
这个图像比之前好看许多 不仅如此
the details in the image, and that's very important for image analysis, and I can
我们还可以看到很多图像中的细节 这在图像分析中非常重要
do simple things like thresholding. So everything that's happened here is
我们可以做像阈值处理这样简单的操作
extremely, extremely simple operations. By the way, this is this.
这里用到的都是极其简单的运算 顺便提一下 这里用到这个变换运算
Going from here to here, basically, is also.
从这里到这里同样用到了一个非常简单的运算
A very simple operation. We actually saw it before.
实际上我们之前看到过这个运算
It's an operation of this tie. Okay?
这里用到的是这个运算
So, this is S, this is R. The sum of the pixel values go to zero if
所以这里是s 这里是r
they are below this particular value. And if they are above, they go to the
如果像素值低于某一个特定值 那么它们就会变成0
maximal value that they can display in the image.
而有些高于这个值 那么它们就会变成图像中可以显示的最大值
So very simple operation can do drastic transformations in the image.
所以非常简单的运算却可以在图像中
And very useful transformations in the image.
做非常明显并且非常有用的变换
A couple of additional examples, here. We have, it's kind of a thresh hold, but
这里有一些其它的例子 这个有些像阀值处理
in the mid range. So, basically we say, okay, anybody that
但只是突出了中间区域
goes from zero to A, I want it to be very low.
如果像素值在0到A之间 就让它变成一个很低的值
Everybody that is above B, I wand it to be very low, and everybody in between, I
如果像素值大于B 也变成一个非常低的值
want it to be very high. And, this is another example.
而在中间的值变得非常高 这里是另外一个例子
Basically everybody between zero and eight, don't touch.
如果像素值在0和A之间 那么就保持不变
Everybody above B, don't touch. Everybody between A and B make it very,
像素值大于B 也保持不变
very bright, or I could say, make it very, very dark, okay?
而令像素值在A和B之间的变得非常亮 或者也可以非常非常暗
So let's assume that you have information that the pixel values of your region of
假设 我们感兴趣的区域
interest are between A and B and you want them to be highlighted in the image, then
像素值在A和B之间 并且我们想要强调这个区域
you do this type of operation or this type of operation.
大家就可以做这种运算 或者这种运算
Let's just see the effects of that in the next slide.
我们在下一张幻灯片中看一下它们的效果
This is the original image here. And this is the first operation, where we
这是原图像 这是第一种运算
basically take a wrench of the image, and that wrench of the image we'll make very
我们来选取图像的一个区域 使其非常亮
brighter. Very bright, everything else, we'll make
让其它所有区域都非常暗
very dark. And this is another example.
这是另外一个例子
This is the second example where we take a region of the image.
这是第二个例子 我们选取图像中一个区域
And we only change that region of the image.
并且只改变图像中的这个区域
Everything else basically stays the same. Of course, you need information.
其它所有区域都保持不变
What's the region that I care of. And that comes, as I say, from
当然 我们需要知道要被关注的区域在哪 像我之前说的 这就是需要从经验中得来的
experience. Offer information about the sin that
或是从我们捕捉的景物信息中得到
you're capturing. In this case.
在这个例子中
Basically, information about the biology and what kind of pixel values.
就是指有关生物学的信息
This region of the image appears. And that's a region that I'm going to
还有这个区域在图像中是用哪些像素值表示的
basically say that I need to make it brighter or I to make it darker and
这便是我们要变亮或者变暗的区域
similarly here. The, the goal of this is to illustrate
这里也是一样的 这里我是想要给大家展示
how very, very simple operations can get us basically what we want.
我们如何利用极其简单的运算达到目的
Can get us to improve the visual appearance of the images, going from very
来改善图像的视觉效果
dark or very bright to very uniform and nice looking images or can help us to
将非常暗或者非常亮的区域 变为像素值分布非常均匀 并且清晰的图像
basically highlight the region of interest.
这些运算还能帮助我们突出感兴趣的区域
If you want to do the analysis of this region in the image, maybe it's nice to
如果大家想要在图像中这个区域做分析
basically make everything as dark. So I can concentrate my attention here.
那么可以将其它区域都变得非常暗 这样注意力就会被集中到这里
But maybe you say, yes. But I lost details, because you made
但或许大家会觉得 这样会丢失图像中的细节
everything white. You say, okay.
因为这个区域都变成白色了
Then let's do something else. Let's just take the whole.
我们也可以做些其它的变换
Background, basically, and make it zero. But let's not change this range of
我们可以将整个背景变成0 但不改变这个区域的值
values. And this is the type of operation that
这里显示的就是这种运算
appears here. We make everything that we don't like
我们将所有不感兴趣的区域 变得非常暗或者非常亮
just very dark or very bright. But everything we care, we leave
但是所有我们感兴趣的地方都保持不动
untouched. And then we can actually.
这样我们就能
Concentrate our visual observation with concentrate only on that region.
只将目光集中在那个区域
So these are very simple operations. In the next video we're going to start
所以这都是一些非常简单的运算 下一个视频我们会开始
talking about histogram equalization but before that, let's just make a short
讲解直方图均衡化 但在这之前
video that basically run some of these operations in real time so we can see how
我们会做一个简短的视频 来实时运行这里的一些运算
simple they are and we can actually observe how they are working on our
这样我们就可以看到它们是多么简单 同时观察它们在图像上的效果
images. So see you on the next video.
下个视频再见
Thank you.
谢谢大家